So this is a question about right
speech. This person asks, "Well, I want
to speak truthfully and with kindness,
but in difficult
conversations, I either speak too
harshly or remain silent out of fear of
conflict. Maybe I'm just overthinking
this, but how can I skillfully apply
right speech in such moments?" Well, by
skillfully applying right actions
beforehand with your body. So is your
mind restrained, entained,
contained, able to endure things on the
right level without acting
out? Then the the field of development
of your speech can become more apparent.
Now it's just you just want to deal with
the speech because that's the acute
issue. But failing to understand that
that the sole reason you swayed as much
in these experiences is because the mind
is not tamed enough, not contained
enough. So you can't be purifying your
speech if your actions are not purified.
Basically, that's what I'm saying.
Because when speaking to others in a
difficult situation, that's pretty
intense. Yeah. And you are unable to
contain that intensity without spilling
out through your mouth.
And the reason you're unable to contain
intensity is because you haven't trained
in containing intensities.
Intensities of restraint and precept.
That's the whole point of containing a
physical behavior is to be able to like
remove uh remain unmoved in face of a
pressuring mind. Mind that exerts
intensity on you to to do to act to say
to think.
So, so then a sign of progress would be
a person who is able to endure harsh
speech. Exactly. Not like a person who
doesn't feel the intensity. You'll still
feel it. Feels the intensity, but it
does not make you say things. Harsh
things. Yeah. Yeah. You're still kind.
You can say kind things or appropriate.
Yeah. In the right way. Either way, or
even if you don't say anything, at least
you won't be saying anything out of that
density, out of that pressure.
And there's really no bypass because you
can learn skillful ways of speaking in
difficult situations, you know,
nonviolent communication and so on.
Yeah. But all that is just to manage the
fact that you still have to do something
on account of that intensity. You're
already freaking out and now you have to
manage to manage it. That's so often in
the sutras like it would be listed there
like high up uh in the training of the
monks it's like well you know restrained
by the virtue sense restraint moderate
he endures the harsh
words he bears them basically not even
endures on the right level you know and
we talk about it kind of slightly
different um no he bears them he bears the harsh
um no he bears them he bears the harsh
words he bears the elements
So there is it doesn't even matter
whether you're aware of the right level
and what the practice is and this or
that bearing it is already
development of elements and harsh words.
No retoring no speaking back just plain
bearing. If you're able to plainly bear
discomfort you'll be able to endure
things on the right level.
Then the domain of the middle way where
things endure on their own where the
discernment happens where the limiters
are discerned all of that that can
become apparent. But if you can't even
bear elements and words of others means
you still have work to do before you can
endure things on the right
level. Because often people think it's
the same. Oh, enduring things on the
right level is the same just as mindless
bearing. It's not.
It's a bit deeper than it's the middle
way. Patient endurance ki enduring
things on the right level as it's the
it's exactly where the middle way is.
It's where you recognize things arising
on their
own. You see the extent of the intensity
and the pressure they exert your mind
exerts on you and you're unmoved by it.
So you're enduring it as in enduring the
lack of the tameness in this animal in
that particular
instance, but you're seeing the full
extent of it. So, it's on the right
level of your correct right perspective.
But for that, you need to work your way
up. And when you fall from that, when
you lose that perspective, you lose that
right right level, well, you fall back
on being able to bear the intensity of
the animal without compromising your
situation further through your actions.
So, it's a it's a fail
safe. And then when that sort of when
the animal comes down somewhat, you
regain the perspective.
So that's how even when you fail to
endure things on the right level, you're
still held up by virtue, by the
aggregate of virtue, by being able to
bear discomfort elements without
disintegrating. But obviously without
discerning and understanding the nature
of contact, passa, pressure, intensity,
whatever way you want to translate it,
bearing like restraint and virtue and
stuff will never automatically or
mechanically or magically take you to
the level of enduring things on the
right level in terms of having
perspective and not too much, not too
little. No, for that you need to
discern. But obviously there will be no
discernment taking place if you're not
even able to practice
basic bearing of the mental pressure
that precepts put on you uh elements
words of others i.e. bearing not acting
out. So there's obviously some overlap
in that development. It's not like black
and white bearing becomes enduring but
it's not the same thing. So that leads
me to another another
question before
his awakening. The bodhic sattva
practiced extreme aceticism and later
said it was futile. The Buddha later
said that was futile. Yet it seems to me
like it was necessary in some way for
him to go through that like it it did
benefit him in some way. Could he have
realized that dama without those years
of kind of hardship, you know? Well, um
it was necessary for him in a sense that
he had to go through trial and
error in order to arrive at that which
was left that middle
way. That's why it was
necessary. Was it necessary in terms of
specifically doing that? No, absolutely
not. That was not necessary. So having
um through trial and error arrived at
neither too much nor too little he then
taught that as the way to
that as the way to
enlightenment to those now who can
practice on account of his teaching. So
basically it was necessary for him
because he was the
first to work his way towards
enlightenment just by himself
internally and that's why he was sama
Buddha self-enlightened
Buddha subsequently everybody else
cannot be that so with the right
instruction that he conveyed
then doing those
things. It's completely
unnecessary. However, where the line of
aeticism is, that's not something that's
just like universally true for
everybody. That depends on a person.
That's why if you know what the middle
way is, if you know where the enduring
things on the right level
is, that's your tune, so to speak.
That's the melody. That's the the the
the the
[Music] the harmony you want to be protecting
the harmony you want to be protecting
and cultivating. Sometimes
increasing aseticism what can be perceived as
aseticism what can be perceived as
aeticism externally
uh can contribute to maintenance of that
middle way of that right
level. Sometimes increasing asetic
practices can actually be detrimental to
it.
So that's why when when devat was
requesting from the Buddha to make these
aesthetic dutangas mandatory for
everybody because they're effectually
inspiring to people make everybody want
to practice that like for future
generations. He said no let those who
want to do it do it and those who don't
want to do it not do it. In other words,
let those let those who know that it's
beneficial for their endurance on the
right level, for their middle way, let
them do it. And let those who know that
it's unbeneficial not do it. Because
doing it
blindly will take you away from the
right melody, from the right
tune. You're just saying, well, I'll put
up with hardships and that will give me
that. Yeah. And that's why I say, why?
allow me to or I won't put up with
hardship. Why?
The the
decision whether you do it or not should
be coming from the recognition of where
the practice is, where the right
endurance is. If it's maintaining it,
clarifying it, do it. If it's obscuring
it, taking it away, taking you away from
it, then don't do it. Yes. that you some
people require a certain amount of
stress to keep things in perspective
actually. Exactly. Yeah, some people
require none. But you can't you can't
just predecide that for yourself. How
much is and even as the Buddha himself
before as a bodhisata he went through
all these things and when he pretty much
ran out of options he tried everything
there's nothing that he hasn't
tried. So that was necessary for him to
then revisit and remember his um um John
experience before he left the household
life.
like he would not have even considered
it if there were still things that were
left for him that he hasn't tried
towards enlightenment and by the way
since we had that um talking about it I
think like the common common notion is
oh he experienced Janna as a child or
something but it's completely
unsupported by sutas I think that came
with like jatikas and later commentaries
I don't know exactly where the whole
idea of he was a young boy under the
tree entering Janna kind of just
spontaneously. It was like innocence of
a child. Yeah. Yeah. Kind of. So
basically kind of and it I think it came
well almost certainly came from the
commentaries but I think it it became
almost like a pivotal point for the
modern views of the special experiences
in meditation in Janna because look it
happened to the Buddha randomly as a
child without restraint without
understanding sensuality and stuff and
no suit ever says that. He says he
remembers under an apple tree before in
his life that he um experienced this and
how about I pursue that and see where it
takes me. Yeah. Um and uh there is no
mention that he was a a child and then
there was the
um uh was it Agam or some Tibetan
parallels to that? I think it might have
been a some other Tibetan or Chinese
parallel um to that uh one of the sutas that
um to that uh one of the sutas that
mentioned that and it elaborates on that
whole story whereby not just that he wasn't a
story whereby not just that he wasn't a
child it was shortly before him leaving
the household life after basically he
already seen a sick a dead sick man old
man and a dead man. So he already his
mind already fully
experienced this passion because there's
actually a suta in Palinikaya where it
says that while he was still a bodhis
satwa before he left his home after
encountering the sick uh aging and dead
man the intoxication with life
sensuality youth left him even before he
went out and became a renunciate to seek
enlightenment. Right. So, so this um
this Chinese parallel elaborates
actually on that story whereby his
father has already had suspicions that
he wants to leave the kingdom and become
a renit wandering aesthetic.
So he sent him to this village that was
under there kind of
um how do you call rulership rulership
uh basically to incite incite him to
rule because that it's going to be his
all of the people there are his subjects
of his kingdom and he should go and
attend to the work they were doing and
just basically get him reinvolved.
So he went there and then uh he saw all
these kind of slaves and and people just
just uh suffering working hard in a very
rough conditions and he says who do you
belong to like who is like says we
belong to you sir like we work for your
kingdom we are yours and then he says
okay well from now from this day onwards
you're free men just leave and he
basically he was so shocked to see the
the the harshness of of your average
person's life he went basically he
dismissed them and went under a tree
under a rose apple tree or whatever is
translated dispassionate completely
dispassionate even more turned away from
the life and that's where he enter Janna
so that's what he remembered after
trying all these extremely amplified
practices of aeticism and this and that
to get he realized hold on I remember
that experience when actually there was
no hindrances
The right level was there. The perfect
tune was just ongoing and it was on the
basis of complete dispassion and
disenchantment. There was nothing tying
him to the world. How about I pursue
that further? And then he realized
that's the way to
enlightenment because up until that
point, see all the aesthetic
practices, they require passion. And he
didn't question that because he thought
those practices are valid in and of
themselves and they'll do the work for
him. But there is no way you will be
committing to the extreme levels of
selfmodification without the that that
that hard center of of
passion driving
you. You need you need it.
But he remembered the experience when
his mind was completely passionless,
completely disenchanted, turned away, not leaning
disenchanted, turned away, not leaning
onto
anything and that was the experience of
China. So that's like although it's some
like a I said Tibetan or a Chinese
parallel, it ties in with that other
actual suta where he did say that these
intoxications left him even before he
left the home. So he was already free
from centrality basically. He said since
he left the home he hasn't had a central
thought even way before he became the
Buddha. So just to kind of reustrate
that point so people don't think these
things happen magically um because some
later commentary there thought oh he
must have been a kid or something. He
just didn't understand what had happened
or he didn't well he didn't understand
the full extent of it. uh and as I said
like he obviously thought that the
aesthetic practices this amplified drive
force and committing to the practices is
more of that dispassion that he was
doing under the apple tree but when he
realized that it isn't just the opposite
yeah he thought oh that was too much see
sensuality connection to the world
concern with the world abandon all of
that you reach the middle level of
dispassion
in regard to both directions. But then
he thought abandoning the world is good.
So how about I go even further and start
forcing this so I get to that
enlightenment and came to the brink of
death and realized hold on actually no
now there's passion again so let me go
back retrace my step until there is no
passion and stop there and there was the
first Janna there was the rose apple
tree experience that was enduring things
on the right level and now he stick to
that and that's then what he thought
what he was teaching afterwards um for
the rest of his
How to get to that through the noble for
path and stay there and protect it and
cultivate it until your work is done.